Haziq Jamil



View this CV online at

haziqj.ml/cv

2020

I am an **Assistant Professor of Statistics** at *Universiti Brunei Darussalam* (UBD). My expertise lie in statistical methodology and computation, with applications towards the natural and social sciences.

I am passionate about bringing data and technology to the forefront of our daily interaction with the world. Using the R programming language, I build statistical models for data analysis in order to gain insights, make predictions, and aid decision-making. I am frequently engaged in cross-disciplinary research collaborations and statistical consultations.

Research Interests

Latent variable models Structural equation models

Binary and multinomial probit Spatio-temporal models

Hedonic pricing models

Bayesian estimation

Gaussian processes

Education

2014 — 2018 PhD in Statistics, London School of Economics and Political Science

Supervisors: Wicher Bergsma1 and Irini Moustaki2

Thesis: Regression modelling using priors depending on Fisher information

covariance kernels (I-priors)3

2013 — 2014 MSc in Statistics (distinction), London School of Economics and Political Science

2006 — 2010 BSc & Master in Mathematics, Operational Research, Statistics and Economics (first class honours), University of Warwick

Supervisor: David Firth4

Dissertation: The analysis of paired comparison data using Bradley-Terry models

with applications to football data

Awards & honours

Teaching Excellence Award in the Sciences, Universiti Brunei Darussalam

Arnold Zellner Thesis Award in Econometrics and Statistics (honourable

mention) 5, American Statistical Association (Business and Economic Statistics

Section)

2013 — 2018 In-Service Training Scheme Scholarship, Public Service Commission, Prime

Minister's Office, Brunei

2006 — 2010 Supreme Commander of The Royal Brunei Armed Forces Scholarship 6, Ministry

of Defence, Brunei

Employment

Mathematical Sciences, Faculty of Science, Universiti Brunei Darussalam7

I teach SM-1402 Basic Statistics, SM-2302 Software for Mathematicians, SM-4331 Advanced Statistics, SM-4335 Advanced Probability, and CU-0304 Sciences for University Study. I also supervise mathematics students' final year projects. In addition to my teaching duties, I am the current Postgraduate Coordinator (Mathematics). I previously held the post of Discovery Year8 advisor (2019-2021).

2014 — 2018 Graduate Teaching Assistant

Department of Statistics, London School of Economics and Political Science9

I held various teaching roles ranging from secondary teaching to marking for masters (ST416 Multilevel Modelling, ST421 Development in Statistical Methods) and undergraduate level courses (ST312 Applied Statistics Project) at the LSE. In addition, I also held assistant invigilator and examiner roles for both the LSE and the University of London International Examinations respectively.

2010 — 2014 Research Officer

2018 — 2019 Centre for Science and Technology, Research and Development (CSTRAD), Ministry of Defence, Brunei 10

I provided analytical insight into matters arising from strategic procurement activities of the Royal Brunei Armed Forces (RBAF). This entailed market research, cost-benefit analyses, and writing technical reports. I was a core team member for the procurement and delivery of 12 Sikorsky S-70i helicopters 11 (US\$325M), and also the focal point for the development of tender evaluation criteria using the Analytic Hierarchy Process.

Service

2020 — present Ad-hoc Reviewer

Annals of Applied Statistics 12; Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C13

2020 — present Review Editor

Frontiers in Applied Mathematics and Statistics 14

2020 Guest Lecturer

Universiti Teknologi Brunei 15

2014 — 2015 MSc Programme Facebook Administrator

Department of Statistics, London School of Economics and Political Science Acted as student liaison for incoming cohort of MSc Statistics 2015/16.

2013 — 2015 **Auditor**

Brunei Down's Syndrome Association (ABLE)16

Consultancy

2017 — 2018 **Data Analyst**

Universiti Brunei Darussalam

Project: The unmet needs of cancer carers in Brunei Darussalam.

| | | Project: Human performance optimisation |
|-------------|--------|---|
| | | Grants and funding |
| 2021 — | - 2024 | Extension of I-prior methodology to nominal response models (~BND 7,000), Faculty of Science Research Grant, <i>Universiti Brunei Darussalam</i> . Role: <i>Principal Investigator</i> |
| 2021 — | - 2023 | Examining spillover effects in regional trading blocs (~BND 17,000), School of Business and Economics Research Grant, <i>Universiti Brunei Darussalam</i> . Role: <i>Member</i> |
| 2021 — 2024 | | Mathematical Modeling of Genetic Assimilation (~BND 8,000), Faculty of Science Research Grant, Universiti Brunei Darussalam. Role: Co-Principal Investigator |
| 2023 — | - 2024 | Predictive potential of graphical descriptors for QSPR/QSAR model learning of compounds (~BND 15,700), Faculty of Science Research Grant, <i>Universiti Brunei Darussalam</i> . Role: Co-Principal Investigator |
| | | Research output |
| | | Articles (peer-reviewed) |
| 2023 | A11 | Importance of Baseline Assessments: Monitoring of Sungai Brunei River's Water Quality O. Onifade, N. Shamsuddin, H. Jamil, D. T. C. Lai, S. Gödeke H2Open Journal (to appear) |
| | A10 | Extremal hyper-Zagreb index of trees of given segments with applications to regression modeling in QSPR studies S. Hayat, M. Adil Khan, A. Khan, <i>H. Jamil</i> , M. Yasir Hayat Malik Alexandria Engineering Journal, 80(1) pp.259–268 |
| | A09 | Statistical significance of valency-based topological descriptors for correlating thermodynamic properties of benzenoid hydrocarbons with applications S. Hayat, N. Suhaili, <i>H. Jamil</i> Computational and Theoretical Chemistry, 114259. DOI: 10.1016/j.comptc.2023.114259 |
| | A08 | The domination number of the king's graph M. Arshad, S. Hayat, <i>H. Jamil</i> Computational and Applied Mathematics, 42(251). DOI: 10.1007/s40314-023-02386-8 |
| 2022 | A07 | Factors Affecting Readmission to a Drug Rehabilitation Centre F. Jali, E. Leong, <i>H. Jamil</i> |

Journal of Population and Social Studies, 30, 591-601.

2021 — 2022

Statistical Modelling Ministry of Defence, Brunei

| A06 | Iron and Manganese Mobilisation due to Dam Height Increase for a Tropical Reservoir in South East Asia S. Gödeke, H. Jamil, M. Schirmer, A. Bretzler, N. Shamsuddin, N. H. Mansor Environmental Monitoring and Assessment, 194(5), 358. |
|-----|---|
| A05 | Pairwise likelihood estimation for confirmatory factor analysis models with categorical variables and data that are missing at random M. Katsikatsou, I. Moustaki, <i>H. Jamil</i> British Journal of Mathematical and Statistical Psychology, 75(2) 23-45. Wiley Top Downloaded Article 2021 |
| A04 | Advocating Blended Learning for University Undergraduate Level Mathematical Instruction Beyond Covid-19 H. Jamil, H. M. Ramli, E. Leong In: Engineering and Sciences Teaching and Learning Activities: New Systems Throughout COVID-19 Pandemics, pp. 33-45. Ed. by Samsul Ariffin Abdul Karim and Saiful Azmi Hussain. Studies in Systems, Decision and Control, vol 381. Cham: Springer. ISBN: 978-3-030-79613-6. |
| A03 | Latent Class Analysis: Insights about design and analysis of schistosomiasis diagnostic studies A. Koukounari, <i>H. Jamil</i> , E. Erosheva, C. Shiff, I. Moustaki PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases, 15(2), e0009042. |
| A02 | Bayesian Variable Selection for Linear Models Using I-Priors H. Jamil, W. Bergsma In: Theoretical, Modelling and Numerical Simulations Toward Industry 4.0, pp. 107–132. Ed. by Samsul Ariffin Abdul Karim. Studies in Systems, Decision and Control, vol 319. Singapore: Springer. ISBN: 978-981-15-8986-7. |
| A01 | Regression modelling using priors depending on Fisher information covariance kernels (I-priors) H. Jamil PhD Thesis. London School of Economics and Political Science. Arnold Zellner award, honourable mention (top 3) |
| | Working papers (preprints and unpublished reports) |
| W09 | Composite likelihood goodness-of-fit testing for binary factor models under simple random and complex survey sampling H. Jamil, I. Moustaki, C. Skinner Manuscript in preparation |
| W10 | Additive interaction modelling using I-priors W. Bergsma, H. Jamil ResearchGate preprint. DOI: 10.13140/RG.2.2.21861.88804. |
| W07 | An Exploratory Investigation on Foreign Language Anxiety among English for |

Islamic Studies Learners in Brunei Darussalam

N. Noorashid, H. Jamil Manuscript in preparation

W08 Patterns of metabolic thermal independence in marine gastropods: A metaanalytical assessment

M. Akram Ullah, D. Marshall, H. Jamil Manuscript in preparation

2021

2020

2018

2023

| 2021 | W06 | I think I understand: Investigating misconceptions regarding hypothesis test concepts among university students A. Zaini, H. Jamil, E. Leong EdArXiv. DOI: 10.35542/osf.io/dj6x9 |
|------|-------|--|
| 2020 |) W05 | Regression modelling with I-priors: With applications to functional, multilevel and longitudinal data W. Bergsma, H. Jamil arXiv:2007.15766 [math, stat]. |
| | W04 | Investigating the effect of load carriage on soldiers' performances using Bayesian structural equation models H. Jamil, A. Salleh, L. Thieng Chan |
| 2019 | 9 W03 | iprior: An R Package for Regression Modelling using I-priors H. Jamil, W. Bergsma arXiv:1912.01376 [stat]. |
| 2017 | 7 W02 | Discussion contribution W. Bergsma, <i>H. Jamil</i> TI Cannings, RJ Samworth (2017). Random-projection ensemble classification. JRSSB, 79.4, pp. 959-1035. |
| 2010 |) W01 | Analysis of paired comparison data using Bradley-Terry models with applications to football data H. Jamil Masters Thesis. University of Warwick. |
| | | Software |
| 2021 | S4 | R/iprior: Regression Modelling using I-priors H. Jamil CRAN 0.7.3 downloads 35K |
| 2020 |) S3 | stat-tables: Open-source statistical tables for use in examinations, tests, and assignments H. Jamil release v0.2 downloads 740 |
| 2018 | 3 S2 | R/ipriorBVS: Bayesian Variable Selection using I-priors H. Jamil release v0.1.1 |
| | S1 | R/iprobit: Binary and Multinomial Probit Regression with I-priors H. Jamil release v0.1 |
| | | Talks |
| | | Further information regarding the following events are available at haziqj.ml/talk |
| 2023 | 3 T18 | International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), University of Maryland, USA Pairwise likelihood goodness of fit tests for binary factor models |
| 2022 | 2 T17 | Teaching and Learning Centre Workshop, UBD, Brunei Quality Typography in Teaching Material: An interactive introduction to LaTeX |
| | | |

| | T16 | Department of Statistics and Data Science Seminar , NUS, Singapore Regression modelling using I-priors |
|------|------|--|
| | T15 | International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), University of Bologna, Italy Selecting interaction effects in additive models using I-priors |
| 2021 | T1 / | |
| 2021 | T14 | MINDEF Scholars Sharing Session, Online Life After MINDEF |
| 2020 | T13 | IADA Seminar, UBD, Brunei A latent variable model for maximal performance testing with dropouts for military applications |
| | T12 | Social Statistics Group Meetings , LSE, London, UK Investigating the effect of load carriage on soldiers' performances using structural equation models |
| 2019 | T11 | UBDSBE Seminar Invitation , UBD, Brunei Bayesian Variable Selection for Linear Models |
| | T10 | CSTRAD Sharing Session , Ministry of Defence, Brunei Misconceptions in Demography |
| 2018 | T09 | FOS Research Seminar, UBD, Brunei A Brief Guide to Variational Inference |
| | Т08 | Inaugural Workshop on Data Science Theory and Practice , LSE, London, UK Binary and Multinomial Regression using Fisher Information Covariance Kernels (I-priors) |
| | T07 | Social Statistics Group Meetings , LSE, London, UK A Beginner's Guide to Variational Inference |
| 2017 | T06 | Turing Data Study Group , The Alan Turing Institute, London, UK Can data science help identify potential drivers of extremism? |
| | T05 | International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), University of Zürich, Switzerland Regression Modelling with I-Priors |
| | T04 | Department of Statistics PhD Presentation Event , LSE, London, UK Binary probit regression with I-priors |
| 2016 | Т03 | Social Statistics Group Meetings , LSE, London, UK I-priors in Bayesian Variable Selection: From Reproducing Kernel Hilbert Spaces to Hamiltonian Monte Carlo |
| 2015 | T02 | Postgraduate Research Seminar, LSE, London, UK Two-stage Bayesian variable selection for linear models using I-priors |
| | T01 | Department of Statistics PhD Presentation Event, LSE, London, UK Regression Modelling using I-priors |

Skills

- Programming, data analysis and visualisation using R, BUGS/JAGS, Stan, Stata, Mplus, and Mathematica
- Reproducible research using Quarto, R Markdown, LaTeX, Git and AWS EC2
- Web development using HTML, CSS, Hugo, GitHub Pages and Netlify

Made with the R package pagedown. The source code is available from github.com/haziqj/cv. Document last rendered on 2023-10-29 17:04:19.026396 [UTC].

Links

- 1. http://stats.lse.ac.uk/bergsma/+
- 2. http://stats.lse.ac.uk/moustaki/←
- 3. https://phd.haziqj.ml/↔
- 4. http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/statistics/staff/academic-research/firth/←
- 5. https://community.amstat.org/businessandeconomicstatisticssection/new-item/new-item2←
- 6. https://scholarship.mindef.gov.bn/Theme/Home.aspx↔
- 7. http://fos.ubd.edu.bn/
- 8. https://ubdmaths.github.io/dy/
- 9. http://lse.ac.uk/Statistics/←
- 10. https://www2.mindef.gov.bn/cstrad/ ←
- 11. https://news.lockheedmartin.com/2011-12-13-Sikorsky-Signs-with-Brunei-Ministry-of-Defence-for-Sale-of-S-70iTM-BLACK-HAWK-Helicopters
- 12. https://imstat.org/journals-and-publications/annals-of-applied-statistics/https://imstat.org/journals-and-publications/annals-of-applied-statistics/ https://imstat.org/journals-and-publications/annals-of-applied-statistics/ https://imstat.org/journals-and-publications/annals-of-applied-statistics/ https://imstat.org/journals-and-publications/annals-of-applied-statistics/ https://imstat.org/journals-and-publications/annals-and-publications/annals-and-publications/ https://imstatistics/ https://imstatistics/
- 13. https://rss.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/14679876 <
- 14. https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/applied-mathematics-and-statistics/https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/applied-mathematics-and-statistics/ https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/applied-mathematics-and-statistics/ https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/applied-mathematics-and-statistics/ https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/applied-mathematics-and-statistics/ https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/applied-mathematics-and-statistics/ https://www.frontiersin.org/ <a hre
- 15. http://www.utb.edu.bn/←
- 16. https://www.instagram.com/ablebrunei/ ←